hi everyone welcome to the seventh
lecture of CS 188 for the semester let's
start with a couple of logistics home or
three games has been released it'll be
due on Monday this coming Monday and
just also a reminder that every homework
has three parts that are due
there is the electronic homework there
is the written part and then there is
the self-assessment of the previous
homework for the written and for the
self-assessment make sure to use the
templates that we provide any questions
about that
yes yeah for the self-assessment you can
go into grade scope download a PDF that
you submitted and annotate onto that if
you happen to not submit anything you
can grab the empty template and annotate
that with the differences between what
you had which it would be empty if you
had empty and annotated with everything
we have to show the differences you can
you can annotate it electronically or
you can annotate it on a printout and
then re scan or take pictures but we
want you to use the template format what
do you do it by writing or by directly
electronically
project two games is out in project two
you get to program minimax alpha beta
evaluation functions expected marks
which we'll see today for pac-man to
play against ghosts this will be due
next week Friday at 4 p.m. also there's
an update to the homework policy we
already posted this on Piazza but I
don't think we've set it in lecture yet
there's 11 homeworks total which is more
than usual you also have 3 parts to each
homework which is more than we've done
in the past so we've concluded it makes
sense to let you drop the two lowest
scoring homeworks so at the end of the
semester will automatically look at
every subset of 9 homeworks and see
which one gives you the highest score
and use that one to compute your
homework grade you can independently
drop written versus electronic versus
self-assessment up to two of each you
don't have to drop them you can just
also do them all but our calculation
will then still just try to grab the
nine highest scoring ones and give you a
grade base and the nine highest scoring
ones for each separately any questions
about that yes say it again
the written homework is graded based on
whether you completed it the our mindset
here is that with the written we want
you to work on it as if it were an exam
would say give yourself a a feeling of
where you would be out if it were an
exam then after that maybe talk with
some other students and write up after
that your full understanding of
everything if it looks like you
completed everything as you would do in
an exam then it's you will get a
complete grade on the written whether
it's accurately solved or not accurately
solved the self-assessment similarly you
will assess what the difference is
between your answer and our answer but
our assessment of your self-assessment
is based on whether your self-assessment
is accurate
not based on whether your
self-assessment gives you a zero or a
five or a ten sorry I couldn't hear that
very well the low what do you mean with
the lowest scores
so what'll happen is at the end of the
semester we'll have been 11 homeworks
and for each one of you that we will
look at your 11 electronic homeworks see
which 9 out of 11 have the highest score
among your 11 and those nine will
constitute your electronic homework
score then we'll look at your 11 written
homeworks we'll look at the 9 out of 11
under the highest score use those as
your written homework score and then
we'll look at your 11 self assessments
and we'll see which 9 out of 11 have the
highest score there and use that as your
self assessment score any other
questions about that mini contest one is
ongoing it's optional it's a lot of fun
though ends on Sunday let's take a look
at the leaderboard at this point so this
is what the contest looks like you'll
have massive mazes compared to the ones
you've done in the regular project
you'll have multiple pacman agents that
work together to clear the board and you
will be time constrained or better
phrase time penalized the more time you
spend thinking about what to do the
lower your score will be let's take a
look at the current leaderboard number
one we have currently
ohto is odo here over there great at
number two we have Jason Lulu here great
and number three we have unison Ian Chen
here and Chen
Thank You Shane wasn't here last time
either but you Shen has a good entry in
the contest and at this point there is a
belief about a hundred forty teams on
the leaderboard some teams have one
student behind that some teams have two
student stu2 students behind it also
some fun names starting to emerge too
greedy
team no sleep don't recommend that a
name for the leaderboard when you're
just too tired to come up with something
jomama key we bought just got some food
delivered should have tried harder and
many more we'll take another look next
time so this will end on Sunday and then
next week we'll report out on the
results of the final ranking and also on
the strategies used by some of the top
teams any questions about the mini
contest ok let's start with the
technical content for today then today
we're going to look at decision making
when there is uncertainty and we'll also
start looking at what these utilities
really are that we've been optimizing
all along since lecture 1 so well now
have uncertain outcomes remember this
game tree from last time where we had a
Maximizer player at the top is to choose
between two actions then the minimizer
gets to choose and we see a 10 and a 10
on the left and 9 in a hundred on the
right if we run minimax what do we end
up with well minimax will say this would
be 10 this would be 9 so we should go
this way and that's what you want to use
if you play against the true minimax
player that really optimizes in this
case against you you want to take no
chances because they're gonna stick you
with a 9 on the other side but we all
salute it - what if you play against
let's say an agent like this one maybe
if the agent looks like that
you say I'm willing to take my chances
there is a possibility that they don't
played the optimal thing for them and
that would give me a hundred and a 9
it's not that much worse than a 10 so
I'm just gonna go for it but I was
pretty informal and the question today
becomes how do we formalize something
like this it could be an agent that
looks like that then you say I'm willing
to take my chances it could also be that
there is inherent
stochasticity somebody's gonna be
rolling dice and based on the outcome of
the roll of the dice go left or right in
that bottom branch if that's the case
and let's say chances is a coin flip
chances are 50/50 you could say well on
average here and we're gonna get 109
divided by two so fifty four point five
on average here I would get ten and now
we have a formal way of justifying going
that way because on average we'll do
better going to the right than going to
the left when we do this kind of
calculation will have a different scheme
of annotating the nodes we'll use
circles so we have up triangles for the
maximizers down triangles for
minimizer's and we will have circles for
chance nodes okay so when we follow this
procedure it's called expecting marks
search might ask yourself the question
why wouldn't we know what the result of
an action would be how come there could
be a chance node in our model of the
world well one possibility is that it's
designed that way maybe we're playing a
game and as part of the game there is
some dice being rolled and then it's by
design stochastic none of possibilities
that the opponents are playing with are
unpredictable
so we don't know how they're gonna act
and maybe we can model them with a
probability distribution over possible
things they might do and we think that
maybe modeling them with a probability
distribution is a better way to model
them than to model them as masterminds
that work against us another reason it
could be it could be that what this is
modeling here is that first you get to
choose between two actions after you
choose those actions those actions don't
get executed perfectly maybe you're a
robot
you want to spin your wheels a bit and
you expect you're gonna move forward or
backward depending on which action you
take but then the wheels might slip and
you might actually not move forward or
might Asha not move backward but instead
stay in place
and then the chance node here would
model the fact that after you chose your
action the outcome of that action is
actually not deterministic now when
we're in this stochastic world our
values should reflect the average case
which is the expect to max value rather
than the worst case or minimax outcomes
we were unexpected max search we will
compute the average score under optimal
play so optimal play here means that you
maximize what you get on average what
does that mean in a game like this one
here you would still if you choose the
right branch always advocate 9 or 100
you would never get the 40 the 54.5
that's never an outcome of the game but
what we're saying is if you were to play
this game many many many times and you
take the right action and it's really
50/50 there then on average you'll get
50 4.5 hence we call the value of the
top node you expect the max value of 50
4.5 even if never we actually
experienced that specific value in any
single outcome of the game how does the
algorithm work well the max nodes are
just like in minimax search nothing
different has to happen chance nodes are
like the min nodes there are opponents
in some sense but they're not working
against us it's just a cast ik and so
rather than saying in a chance now we
take the min like we did for minimizer's
in a chance node we say let's take some
weighted average based on how likely
each outcome is those are called
expectations the weighted average of the
outcomes later will actually see another
formalism that's very related to this
that's gonna start next week called
Markov decision processes which is
another way to think about expected max
problems ok actually let's let's run
some demos illustrating what we're doing
here so as typically in the in the
lectures there's kind of two big parts
to how I think about problems there is
we have the world we want to turn it
into some model that we use
the world and then we have an algorithm
that works on the model and finds a
solution based on that model and so you
can ask the question okay what does it
mean to model the world in a very
specific way for example let's model the
world let's go back to a situation we
had last time over here there Grimm
world again for pac-man flanked by two
ghosts we now have a choice on how to
model this situation we could say we're
going to model it as ghosts that work
directly against us
that would be minimax if we model things
that way then we have a minimax tree
where there is pac-man and each of the
ghosts then pac-man each of the ghosts
this repeats and we're the tree that
goes maybe till the end of the game if
we do minimax search in that tree what
will happen well we saw last time
because we lose a point for every time
step that passes and we again tend for
food pals what we're flanked here and
we're going to be eaten by the ghosts we
might as well be eaten as quickly as
possible
so we're going to go right onto the red
ghost and get eaten as quickly as
possible and that's indeed what minimax
in this case will give us so minimax
inaction goes straight to the nearest
buy ghost minimize the damage what on
the other hand if we set it up as an
expected max tree in expecting max when
the ghosts choose it's a coin flip in
particular for the blue ghost it's a
coin flip whether they'll go up or down
and then they keep going the direction
they chose so if your unexpected max
what do you expect to happen we say well
there's two possible outcomes well
there's many possible outcomes if we if
we go to the right only one thing
happens we die instantly if we go to the
left there is two possible outcomes
either the ghost is running away or
coming to me if it's coming to me
then I'm in trouble and I really should
have dive-bombed the red ghost I would
have finished things off earlier and
lost less points that's a bad outcome
but if the blue ghost is running away
from me then I can run behind the blue
ghost eat all the dots and get high
reward so expect the max will then say
okay if that's a 50/50
thing we now need to average this quarry
again in one case versus the other case
of running to the left and if the
average of that is higher than will you
get from running to the right then you
should run to the left
that doesn't mean after you decide to
run to the left that you're guaranteed
to do better than you would have done if
you had run to the right it's a 50/50
chance and so sometimes you'll do really
well sometimes you'll actually not do
well depends on the random seed let's
see what happens here
expect the max let's run pac-man has
decided needs to go left to maximize
expected value but will it be lucky in
this run or not we'll see it is lucky in
this run and so it gets a very high
score if we run this again we'd expect
to max it might be lucky again or it
might be unlucky this time it's unlucky
and it has a score that's as negative as
it's going to get in this particular
game scenario but on average it's doing
better than even have gone off to the
right and ran into the ghost instantly
one thing that's important to keep in
mind here is that we're making
assumptions about how this goes to
function all right and these assumptions
can be mismatched with the world and we
need to be careful about that if you're
running specta max but the ghost is
actually playing against you then you're
very naive in you're gonna be taken
advantage of on the other hand if you
play minimax but the ghost is cannae
random then you're very pessimistic
about everything too cautious you don't
take advantage of opportunities and so
it's important to understand how the
world functions to then decide which
model are you going to use here's a
pseudo code for this looks a lot like
the minimax pseudo code we had last time
there is a dispatch node The Dispatch
node decides is this a terminal state or
not if it is returned the state's
utility if it's not checked is it a max
call max value is it an expecting node
called the x value function this one is
the same as before then the one on the
right the expectation calculation is a
weighted average so it loops over all
successors looks at the probability of
that successor and then looks at the
value of that successor multiplies with
the probability of having that successor
and computes the weighted sum of all of
them so let's take a look at this in
action here is a X node we have
probabilities that are not equal in this
case 1/2 1/3 1/6 so that means we end up
with 1/2 8 plus 1/3 24 plus 1/6 negative
12 which is t4 plus 8 minus 2 is 10 so
we have 10 over here and again very
different from minimax is done in
minimax whatever ended up over here
correspondent is something we had at the
bottom here there's no 10 at the bottom
you're never gonna have 10 but on
average you expect to score 10 if you
land in this node
let's do another example maybe let's
have you work for this one give you 30
seconds talk to your neighbors and
figure out what is the expected max
value that is the value of this node
over here in this game tree
all right any thoughts on the value of
the game here
anyone suggestion is eight anybody have
another suggestion
everybody thinks eight seems right how
will we get it
well it wasn't explicit here when it's
not explicit we tend to assume that all
probabilities are equal but then we
could sometimes have them not be equal
but we're assuming they're all equals
nothing else is said we have to then
equally average these three plus 12 plus
nine is 24 divided by 3 is 8 2 4 6
divided that's 12 divided by 3 is 4 21
divided by 3 is 7 then we have a max
node on top of that max node will choose
the maximum expected value which is 8 so
we had it right now last time when we
looked at minimax after we saw minimax
we saw some modifications of minimax
that could make it more practical for
example we saw alpha beta pruning which
was a meta reasoning approach that
allowed us to think about is this
subtree important to look at or it
doesn't maybe not even matter what's in
this subtree it's not going to affect
the outcome of what the value is of this
game can we do the same thing here we
haven't expected max tree we've seen the
left branch to be 8 so we know that we
have an option of 8 going this way we
now see a 2 over here can we now skip
the rest or not see some knows why not
well you can't know right now it doesn't
look pretty good with the 2 but what if
one of these is 1 million over here all
of a sudden looks really good and you
want to go there of course you still
need to check none of the other ones are
negative 1 billion but it really matters
to look until the last one because when
you average things out one really
extreme number can always dominate the
average and so you can't skip anything
in this scenario unless you know there
are maybe some bounds on what values can
be achieved
at the different nodes so can't do the
same kind of pruning the other thing we
looked at was to do a depth limited
search the reason there was that if we
have to traverse the tree even with
alpha beta pruning where we only need to
look at in best-case scenario square
root of the size of the tree square root
of the size of the tree is still often
way too big to visit everything so can
we maybe look at less by making
approximations and in depth limited
search we made the approximation that we
said we're not going to search all the
way to the bottom because we can't get
there in the time we have we're gonna
stop earlier so maybe we stopped
somewhere here we say after three moves
we use an estimate of the true value
using a evaluation function so we look
at the current situation we had an
evaluation function since this situation
we think is worth this much compute that
number and use that instead of looking
underneath that evaluation function is
only going to be an approximation it
might be better if you design a really
good evaluation function whereas if you
don't design a good one a lot of art
goes into that often also machine
learning goes into that if you have seen
many situations before you've seen how
much they were worth you can in
principle machine learn to predict how
much a new situation is worth what it
results in is that you don't need to go
as deep in the tree and you can in a
reasonable amount of time find an
approximate answer to the value at the
top okay how about these probabilities
that we're using now let's do a little
bit of a refresher of what they are and
then build up from there a random
variable represents an event whose
outcome is unknown and the probability
submission is an assignment of weights
to those outcomes for example we might
decide that we don't know what the
traffic is on the freeway or baybridge
right now
we don't know what it is but we still
want to somehow reason about it and so
we're going to assign probabilities to
different possible situations we might
say 25% chance it's empty it's broad
enough the Bay Bridge then is something
else
50% chance the highway has mild traffic
and 25% chance it has heavy traffic
a lot of modeling assumption being made
here for one we just assumed that
traffic can take on only three values
that's a very specific assumption of how
we're modeling the world here you might
say I'm gonna measure density with real
numbers or you might say I'm gonna model
it in five categories those are choices
you have to make as the engineer the
designer of your AI system how do you
want to capture what is in the world and
then the second thing we have to do is
choose probabilities for each one of
them and the choice of those
probabilities will affect what we do
when we run an expected max agent
because if the probabilities are
different then different outcomes are
more or less likely making certain
branches better or worse for the agent
but that's what we have to do here for
now there are some laws of probability
they're always non-negative and they
have to sum up to one so notice that
some of all of these is one it's also
the case that as we get more information
maybe over the lifetime of the agent the
probabilities can change for example
maybe a priori we think probability of
heavy traffic is 25% but now we know
that it is 8:00 a.m. well if we know
it's 8:00 a.m.
probability of heavy traffic is higher
because a lot of people are driving
around 8:00 a.m. and now the probability
has changed to be 0.6 we'll talk more
about that later the middle one third of
the class is very much focused on
dealing with probabilities updating them
based on new evidence that comes in and
so we'll defer that to them but for now
just keep in mind that these
probabilities are things we need to work
with and that they can change as you get
more information what does it mean to
compute an expectation the expected
value of a function of a random variable
the average weighted by the probability
distribution over outcomes so how long
does it get to the airport how long to
get to the airport if this is our
distribution over traffic and maybe
depending on the the traffic situation
it could be 20 minutes 30 minutes or 60
minutes then the expected value of
travel time to the airport would be the
weighted sum which gives us 35 minutes
any questions about this this kind of
the basic review we're doing yes okay so
the question is what did the expected
value is the same in both branches but
maybe in one branch you have it it'll be
either 500 or 550 whereas the other one
would have something closer to zero in a
thousand and that's how much higher
variance might have a preference for one
or the other we'll touch upon some of
that at the end of this lecture
so let's defer it out for now but it's a
good consideration
so and expect the max search we have a
probabilistic model of how the opponent
or the environment will behave in any
state this model could be as simple as a
uniform distribution roll of dice model
could be sophisticated and require a lot
of computation you might say it might be
something along the lines of you have to
decide whether to organize a barbecue or
a indoor event maybe October 10th and
then maybe you run a complicated
simulation of air pressure air flows and
from that you have a distribution over
what the weather will be like on that
day and then you use that distribution
to decide whether one or the other is
the better decision and so that can
often happen in practice that the way
you get those probabilities is after
very complicated calculation and then
finally you know what the probabilities
are in the game tree there's a chance
node for any such stochastic event where
we don't have control it could be
opponent or it could be environment and
it might even be that our probabilistic
model says that it's likely the ghosts
are adversarial to us but they're not
necessarily always adversarial to us
that's one type of probabilistic model
where you say maybe they're mastermind
goes working directly against us maybe
not maybe some probability for one
similarly for the other for now we
assume each chance node magically comes
along with probabilities so probability
fairy visits us for this lecture
sprinkles the probabilities and we're
good to go
one thing to keep in mind though is that
even though this is how we model things
it doesn't need to mean that we are
right for example you might model a
opponent as some probability of being
minimax and some probability of being
random but it doesn't mean the opponent
is actually doing any such things it's
just your model that you put in this
expected max tree and hopefully your
model is related to what is happening in
the real world
for example maybe
you're playing against someone and you
don't have enough information to know
how they play you don't have their
strategy and then you might have a
distribution over strategies and
practice they have one strategy and
they're using it but you don't know what
the strategy is and so you can have a
distribution over strategies and
optimize against a distribution over
strategies rather than a single strategy
let's do another little exercise let's
say you know that your opponent is
actually running a depth - minimax and
uses the result 80% of the time and the
other 20% of the time doing a random
move to mix things up how would you put
this into a game tree I'll give you
about maybe a minute to think about this
talk with your neighbors and let's see
what you come up with
okay any thoughts about how we can model
this over there yes
so the suggestion here is because we
know the opponent periodically makes a
random move we don't want to play too
conservatively and so we want to somehow
built into what we do that we don't end
up playing too conservatively now of
course the question is how do we build
that into it
so we know that's what we want based on
analyzing what the description is here
but we want to avoid of course is that
we have to hard-code all kinds of things
into it and we'd like to see if we can
reduce it to a game tree and if we run
search the right kind of search in this
game tree then that strategy that you
want that periodically taking your
chances just automatically emerges from
solving the game tree and so then the
question becomes if you want to achieve
this and you're right we want we do want
to achieve this how do we set up the
game tree such that a search in that
tree gives us what we want suggesting
that in the back there
okay so the suggestion there is if we
reach an opponent node we're going to
model it as eighty percent chance one
type of behavior 20% chance another type
of behavior the 20% chance other type of
behavior in fact we reach a chance node
again because it's random and the 80%
side we reach the minimax strategy of
depth to that the opponent is using and
then once we do that and that's that's
the answer we're gonna follow here is we
achieve a game tree that if we were
unexpected max in that game tree we find
a strategy that takes advantage of the
brandman's in the opponent while also
being aware that it's only random 20% of
the time so the answer remains then
expected max but to run this expected
max when we look at these chance nodes
for each chance node a bunch of
calculation has to happen inside that
chance node before we can proceed so
when we look at one of these chance
nodes what's the probability the
opponent let's say a ghost moving left
or right well we need to then look at
this description here and we actually
need to go from depth room in minimax to
understand what happens 80% of the time
so you need to think about that that
tells us for 80% of the time what's
happening one specific action depth to
minimax solution and then the other 20%
of the time with may be equally ran
equal this probability over all other
actions or maybe even including the one
that's chosen from the depth to minimax
so what we have here then is an whenever
we encounter a chance node we have to do
a whole minimax calculation to just find
the probabilities that live in that
chance node imagine that goes to the
depth 10-minute max then every chance
node you encounter you'd have to run a
depth 10 minimax search which could be
pretty expensive quickly to find the
distribution over actions they would
take so it's kind of interesting imagine
it's indeed depth 10 minima X 80 percent
of it
time and 20 percent of the time just
random action to solve that kind of
problem in every opponent node you have
to run another depth 10-minute max
whereas regular minimax you just have to
do depth then once in the original tree
and you're done what's happening here
why is it so much more expensive to deal
with an opponent that does this other
thing where sometimes they do something
random it's because now we don't have a
perfect match between the assumptions of
one player player a about player B and
player B about player a once these
assumptions are mismatched all of a
sudden that the tree doesn't nicely
aligned in the entire search and you
need to do all these side calculations
and that's what's happening here
whereas in minimax if one is always
minimize other one is always Maximizer
and they know that about each other and
do that consistently then their tree is
the same tree but here it's not anymore
because there's a mismatch and we need
to do a big calculation in each of the
opponent nodes to figure out what they
would do in that situation or
distribution over what they would do any
questions about this yes
so the way we've we set it up here the
assumption is that this is how we model
the opponent so we model the opponent as
doing this what they actually do it
might be that if it is that then we're
doing great by solving it this way if
they're actually doing something else
then doing this is not gonna be the best
fit to play against that opponent but
all we can be sure of in this setting
here is that we have a model for how I
think they behave and if we assume
that's a good model this is how we could
solve the problem question yes in this
case it will take a constant amount of
time longer so it'll be the constant
amount of time that it takes to expand
depth to depth to minimax search and so
maybe that is a certain amount of time
that is a factor I don't know 20 or 100
larger than just already having a chance
node that tells you the distribution
over actions and then that would be
happening throughout the tree that you
have to pay that factor 10 or 100
whenever you consider the opponent
it also shows that in practice you might
have to approximate your opponent
because if you if your opponent is
somehow capable of looking a hundred
deep you might not have the resources to
also look a hundred deep and you'll have
to approximate it with something else
that hopefully is is good enough let's
take a look at the assumptions we're
making throughout here and what are the
dangers of optimism and the dangers of
pessimism what a dangerous optimism it's
assuming chance when the world is
adversarial what does that mean it means
you go around the world you see
everything very rosy everything's good
everything's good and in practice that
might mean you get pickpocketed
everywhere you get mugged everything a
lot of things go wrong because you're
just assuming the world is so good where
it really is not as good as you're
assuming it is and so that's the danger
of optimism you get taken advantage of
by adversaries what's the danger of
pessimism well what does it mean to be
too pessimistic it means that you assume
the worst case when it's actually not
that likely like you see a bunny and you
think it's a vampire button and every
single bunny you see now that gives you
a very very scary life you're constantly
jumping away from things not living very
optimally if they're just kind of little
bunnies more generally what it means
let's look at some examples for pac-man
well we'll do here is we'll look at a
grid of possible scenarios so what do we
have here we have pac-man could play
minimax or play expect to max and the
ghosts could be adversarial or could be
random if the ghost is random and
pac-man plays expect to max that's a
good way to play you're kind of matched
up with how the world works
so let's take a look at that first
random ghost
pac-man plays expect to max and here we
go
ghosts randomly stepped out of the way
pac-man didn't let's watch it again
black man assume that goes to do
something random so wasn't afraid to get
too close and then just ate the one
pallet left and won the game what do you
think is gonna happen in next one where
we have pac-man play minimax and the
ghost is adversarial well either cero
ghost is gonna try to chase pac-man and
pac-man's going to anticipate that and
keep a safe distance and hopefully still
somehow get to the food pellet
you might wonder how come this
adversarial ghost doesn't just protect
the food palate wouldn't that be a
smarter thing to do well that's what an
adversarial ghost would do if they could
look really really far ahead in the game
tree but in practice we can only look so
far ahead
the typical evaluation function for a
ghost is based on distance to pac-man
and so if you only look let's say four
steps ahead and after four steps you're
hoping to be as close as possible to
pac-man then you get this County
behavior where you are constantly trying
to move closer and you might open up the
palate for pac-man to eat and finished
again now let's think about what happens
if we assume well we play expect max but
the ghost is a minimax ghost so the
ghost is playing directly against
pac-man pac-man is playing expecting max
so this is pac-man is too optimistic for
their own good so if you're optimistic
hangs out and just made it on this one
sometimes optimism is good and it works
out sometimes it's less good and so this
will play out stochastic Li because just
the way the game is set up a little bit
of randomness in it and sometimes
pac-man will succeed sometimes be eaten
it's not playing very safe against an
adversarial ghost how about the other
scenario the scenario in the bottom
right here on on bottom right the random
ghost
but then a minimax pac-man minimax means
pac-man assumes the ghost is playing
against it so it's going to play a very
safe assume that ghost has a plan to
come and chase it and eat it and gonna
keep a very safe distance but in reality
the ghost is actually random so the
ghost is just randomly bumping around
pac-man waits off on the left and then
when finally there is room is daring to
go let's look at another one of these
gosu just bopping around pac-man is
worried it's very worried keeps being
worried but it finally says now there is
no mastermind plan that exists anymore
that can get me on the way to the dot
and now I'm willing to go we ran this
quite a few times here at this course we
ended up with so if you want to get
statistically significant scores need to
run more than five times but I think
this gets the picture across if it's a
random ghost and expect to max we get
the highest on average 503 because we're
in an easy environment because the ghost
is not playing against us and we're
aware we're in an easier environment and
taking advantage of it here we're in the
most in a difficult environment and
we're aware of it our score is lower but
not that bad because we realize this is
a difficult environment and we play
accordingly on the other hand if it's a
difficult environment and we're not
aware of it then we often get eaten and
our score is not that great on average
and then over here we have a random
ghost so easy environment but we're not
really taking an advantage of it so we
have a lower score than if we take
advantage of it but not that much worse
in this case because we only waste so
much time being scared before we dare to
go for the food palette any questions
about this
okay so so far we have seen two types of
games we have seen minimax games and
expect the max games there are some
other types still turn based for example
backgammon in backgammon there is a
Maximizer a minimizer and chance and so
effectively it is the same thing we just
now need a dispatch node that can this
pass between terminal max min X and we
can solve these kinds of problems too
for example what happens here its
maximizers turn chooses a move after
that moved there's a roll of dice which
determines the situation minimizer gets
to sea in which they get to make a move
and this process repeats very simple in
terms of algorithmic change just for
weight dispatch instead of 3-way
dispatch backgammon such a pretty big
game in terms of state space Prisma 20
legal moves each time there's a depth if
you do a depth to search then you have
20 moves but there is also this
stochasticity to account for how many
possible outcomes of rolling the dice
and we get actually a very large tree
even if we only look at very small depth
asset depth increases probability of
reaching a given search node shrinks so
what we have happened here is that
because of the stochasticity each
particular branch is in some sense less
significant than it would be in a
minimax scenario because in minimax
maybe opponent could forces down a path
in backgammon the opponent can't really
force us down anything they need to have
the right roll of the dice before they
can forces anywhere and so no single
branch can dominate as much as it can in
minimax historically what that resulted
in - is that for backgammon there's
actually the first AI will champion for
any game this was built with just a
depth to search a very good evaluation
function trained with reinforcement
learning and this achieved world
champion level play and so the intuition
here why you can get away with depth to
search is that if you miss this one
scenario that could happen somewhere
down the tree actually it's not that
likely to happen anyway because of the
averaging that's happening and so just
depth to happens to be enough to build a
world champion there are other types of
games so this is one variation where you
have min max X here we have a multi
agent again so we have a red player a
blue player and a green player what does
this mean it means if we're at a
terminal node here let's pick one where
they're all different numbers if we end
up over here
the utility for red is 7 for green for
blue is 2 for greenness 1 so what we
have here is that each player has their
own value of a terminal node and we'll
optimize for their own outcome minimax
we kind of had that too the Maximizer
had the number that we were showing and
the minimizer had the negative of that
number so we're actually two numbers
sitting there those didn't negative of
each other so we only showed one but
minimax is a special case of this where
we just collapsed those two opposite
numbers into one number that we display
different things can emerge here though
when these numbers are not just
complementary to each other for example
what if we're over here
what would blue want to happen well blue
would love this 6 over here can they
make that happen well what if they play
this way what will green do Green will
look adllaw I could have 6 or 2 Green
will choose 2 6 which will happen that
blue also gets 6 and gets what they want
so we have here is actually a
collaboration between blue and green
happens to emerge because the utilities
they have over outcomes happens to be
aligned in a nice way that they end up
working together that doesn't mean they
are told to work together
it's just emerging from these utilities
if the game ended up over here
what would blue one blue would say well
I'd love to get a seven that's the
nicest thing underneath here let's say
blue goes here
well well Green say well there's a one
here for me in a five year for me I like
the five I'm going here and blue ends up
with two blue really should have gone
this way where Green would have chosen
let's see Ashley not sure if it fully
works out here blue would have preferred
yeah let me retake that one what
happened here on the right is that even
though blue would have preferred seven
Green doesn't pay attention to that and
just picks this one independently what
happens on the left is something very
similar if blue goes here Green will
still not pay attention to what blue
cares about here is a seven here is it
two and green will pick this side and
blue will end up with one and so in both
branches here we see that green because
the opposite of what blue would have
wanted even though on this side they're
perfectly aligned and that's just a
consequence of whatever their utilities
are for the leaf nodes how do we solve a
problem like this in each node we now
look at the values underneath and pass
them all up based on the decision the
current node would make for example
we're here green checks 2 or 6 6 is
better so it's being passed up 1 6 6 is
being passed up here Green says two is
better than one so 6 1 2 is being passed
up then blue takes a look which is the
middle number 6 is better so 1 6 6 is
the value over here similarly on the
other side green decides at the bottom
we'll go for the 7 this is a 5 1 7 the
other one I'll pick the 5 this is a 5 2
5 then blue we'll pick based on the
middle number so it'll be a 5 2 5 and
red will pick on the
first number and so those will be five
to five and this is how the game will
play out so similar machinery as we've
used for min Max and expected nodes but
now keep in mind you need to propagate
values for all players not just a single
value any questions about this okay
let's take a couple minutes break here
and after the break we'll look at
utilities
sure
ok let's restart
ii have a lecture we're going to look at
utilities to think back to lecture 1 the
kind of mantra for the AI class is
maximize your expected utility
we've been maximizing expected utilities
we've not actually looked at those
utilities and where they might come from
and why it's even meaningful to have
them should they even exist and that's
what we're gonna do now so one question
could have why should we average
utilities why not minimax ok let's think
about this let's say you're gonna make a
decision and maybe you're deciding
between I don't know deciding between
pizza and Thai food or something they
might say okay what are my utilities for
each one of them the Thai food is
exciting but it's sometimes too spicy
for me and then you might assign some
utility to it the pizza has some utility
but but the Thai food one has like
different outcome so you can say well
actually maybe use the worst case where
it's too spicy for me and it's gonna be
bad so then Thai food is a worse choice
than pizza and I'm gonna take piece that
I would be the minimax approach to
choosing what you're gonna do but maybe
that's not the right way to do it if
you're constantly afraid of the
worst-case scenario that's the scenario
we talked about everything is a vampire
Bunny in fact what you're then gonna do
is you're never going to go out on the
street you can say there's always some
chance that one of the drivers makes a
mistake drives onto the sidewalk hits me
and you're minimax tells you to stay
inside at all times they don't maybe say
well if you're inside maybe an
earthquake can happen and things can
collapse in you'll just have no
reasonable choices if you run minimax
for all your decisions
the only time minimax can actually be
useful for you is if you already ahead
of time exclude all those really special
things that rarely happen but if you
want to incorporate that these things
can happen these extreme events then
minimax will never work so if you want
to do a fairly comprehensive reasoning
about the world minimax will just not
work for you because you're always
afraid about what's going to happen
okay so then freckles we were down to
something like expected max was the
principle of maximum expected utility is
that the rational agent should choose
the action that maximizes its expected
utility given its knowledge about how
the world works
okay so then the questions are where do
these utilities come from let's think
about that let's say you have a agent
that's supposed to clean your house
where should your utilities for the
agent come from well we should specify
them for that agent we should tell the
agent your utilities based on how clean
the house is we can't just let the agent
choose their own utility if they choose
their own utility they might just say oh
well hi utility in no matter what I'm
just gonna sit here it's easy I'm
optimizing my utility have to do nothing
so to ensure that the agent does
something we care about we gotta be able
to give it the utilities that we wanted
to optimize for so that's where they
come from we have to give him to the
agents but that means that somehow we
have to have utilities that quantify
what we like or don't like about
outcomes in the world so how do we know
that we even have those and that's even
rational to have utilities doesn't even
make sense to think of the world in
terms of every outcome has a utility
associated with it and let's say we do
have a number for every outcome in the
world why is a virgin them the right
thing to do and what if you believe that
your behavior just doesn't match up with
utilities is that possible is it
possible that you just live your life in
a way that utilities are not meaningful
and then maybe you can't use utilities
for your agents to help you out because
it's mismatched with how you live your
life well let's first take a look at
some of the new challenges and expect to
max in terms of utilities compared to
minimax
let's look at these two game trees here
what's different between them is that we
squared the terminal values going to the
right so 0 squared is 0 for T squared is
1600 20 squared is 400 30 squared is 900
now let's see what happens if we run
minimax in both of these trees
well surrounding the first one what do
we end up with well we end up with a
zero here a 20 here so we're gonna play
this way what's gonna happen in the
second tree outcomes going to be the
same because by squaring the leaf nodes
have the same ordering so we have the
same preference over leaf nodes and in
minimax that means we end up with the
same outcome
we'll still min will still prefer going
left there and still prefer going left
here which will make max prefer going
right here the value is now 400 because
we squared everything but the game gets
played the exact same way what if we
have expectant notes there well this
average is 20 this average here is 25 25
is better
we have 25 how about on the other side
the average here is 800 the average on
the other one is 650 so we prefer to 800
and it has changed so by squaring the
utilities we've changed how we play it
again so it means that all of a sudden
one will work with things like expect
them actually average utilities it's not
just about ordering outcomes it's also
about the numbers we associated with
these outcomes because the specifics of
those numbers do matter and affect what
we're going to decide okay so let's look
at some examples our utilities are
functions from outcomes that is states
of the world to real numbers that
describe an agent's preferences for
example maybe there's three possible
outcomes you have a ice cream cone you
have an ice cream cone with one scoop
that's probably better or the ice cream
cone with two scoops which you might
think is even better and so you might
say it's this kind of preference
relationship that's great
but if you want to do expect to max its
not enough to know which outcome is
preferred over which outcome a she need
associated numbers which each one of
those do reason appropriately okay in a
simple game the numbers are easy they're
just the rules of the game will tell you
maybe plus one for a win negative one
for a loss zero for a draw it turns out
there is a theorem that even beyond
games for any rational preferences we
can summarize them with a utility
function and we'll see that theorem in
in a moment okay
so we prefer two scoops over one scoop
over just a cone but when we make
decisions we might not get decide just
being those three there might be
probabilistic outcomes for example we
might get a single or a double single
makes us pretty happy double is more
complex when we get a double we might
drop it much harder to balance and now
we only have two cone all we might
really be happy and have the two scoops
to enjoy now if we need to decide where
did it go for a single or double it
matters what the probabilities are of us
dropping it and it matters what the
actual utility numbers are here it's not
enough to know that two is better than
one is better than zero we need to know
the numbers and the probabilities and
that will determine which choice we make
over here
okay so we need to deal with utilities
of distributions over outcomes outcomes
here the terminology that people use is
prizes don't think about it as some kind
of prize you win for something amazing
you've done it's just terminology you
can just call it outcomes or leaf nodes
in one of those trees and there could be
a prize that's called a one that's
called B and so forth a lottery is a
situation with uncertain prices I would
say expect a node over outcome could be
a or b
and then our notation is that if we
prefer a over B we write this if they're
equally good to us we write this thing
okay now when we talk about lottery
again this is a terminology in this
context that means something specific
this is what it means to be a lottery it
doesn't mean there's some kind of game
involved where you're scratching things
and seeing what's underneath it just
means that a probabilistic event is
going to happen we end up with either A
or B with some probability distribution
okay now let's see what it means to be
rational okay
one thing we want from a rational agent
is that it has transitivity of its
preferences what does that mean if the
agent prefers a over B and prefers B
over C the agent should also prefer a
over C that seems pretty logical can we
make this even more explicit now this is
really the only right way to go in some
sense well we can imagine we have an
agent who does not satisfy this property
then we can essentially acquire all
their money the way this will happen is
that if they don't satisfy the property
let's say they prefer B over C then if
they had C when they start out they
would happily pay a little bit of money
to give us C and an exchange get B and
we'll get one cent along the way by
giving them be and getting see if they
then prefer a over B then they just got
B from us they can give us B now and pay
low extra to get a instead from us and
we again made some money then now if a
now remember we got see from them
initially if they're now I'm transitive
they decide C is better than a and we
have C ready to go and I'll give us a
again with a bit of money because C is
worth more to them now they have C and
we got some money and we're back to
where we started so we went around in
this circle where at the end of it all
that happened is we made 3 cents and
everybody's holding the same prizes as
they were holding in the beginning
so being transitive seems pretty
important otherwise this cycle is going
to be a kind of put into play against
you and you're going to lose everything
overtime what are some other actions
that people have positive rational
agents should satisfy you are required
to either prefer a over B B over a or be
indifferent to them those are the only
three options for two prizes
transitivity we just discussed
continuity if you prefer a over B and B
over C then there must be a lottery
between a and C that is equivalent to B
because b lies between a and C so some
distribution over a and C should match
up with B substitutability if a and B
are equally good to you then a lottery
that involves a with some probability is
equivalent to you to the same lottery
that involves B rather than a
monotonicity says that if you prefer a
over B then if P is a probability that's
higher than Q then a lottery that has
higher probability on a compared to this
one here should be preferable okay
because you prefer a over B you increase
the probability of a and you should
prefer that lottery that has increased
probability of a and decreased
probability of B these all seem pretty
logical that you would want from your
agents there is some theory that shows
that if your agent preferences satisfy
or your preference satisfy these actions
with rationality then your behavior can
be your optimal behavior can be
described as maximization of expected
utility
okay so rationality confirmed if you
satisfy these actions and a more formal
theorem says this that this is the von
Neumann Morgenstern theorem and also
from Ramsey in 1931 given any preference
to satisfying these constraints there
exists a real valued function you the
utility function such that
if your preference is a over B then that
function you will satisfy you of a
bigger than or equal to U of B and the
utility of a lottery will be the
weighted sum of the utility of each of
the entries each of the prizes in the
lottery this is what we're doing an
expected max right the averaging step is
exactly this we're averaging utilities
based on their probabilities so this is
saying that that is a right thing to do
if you have rational preference so if
you want if you're happy with these
actions then the consequence is that
their utility there exists utility
function where averaging is the right
thing to do the maxim expect utility
principles then to maximize that
expected value let's not think about
human utilities because if we're going
to have agents make decisions for us we
need to think about our utilities and
give them to the agent so they can
maximize our expected utility how do you
says util assess utility values for
outcomes one we do is to normalize them
you could say the best possible thing in
the world is a1 and the worst possible
thing in the world is a zero for example
maybe worst thing is being death and
then you could say you can start
quantifying this has things like micro
mort's if you have a 1 million
one-in-a-million chance of death what is
that worth to you to avoid that
okay you start quantifying things that
are extreme because we want to look at
the extremes quality-adjusted life years
is another metric often used it's also
important to keep in mind that we say
there is a utility function consistent
with your preferences you can actually
add a constant to it and rescale it with
a positive scalar and nothing will
change in your behavior because that is
compatible with how averaging operations
also work out okay now if we don't
consider lotteries all we can do when
asking people questions is understand
what they prefer over what and have a
ranking but once we start giving them
lotteries we can start understanding the
actual utility values and that's
we need to do to infer their actual
utility values so here's how we do this
Sanders standard way of getting
somebody's utilities you say okay you
can spin the wheel or pay to pass when
you spin the wheel there's some small
chance it lands on that instant death
that's it okay so nobody would like to
play this game probably but the question
is how much you willing to pay to not
have to play this game and that tells us
something about what let's say this is
worth to you
so best possible prize is in this case
could be life stays as is or something
worst case is you're dead and so the
game would be you could say okay how
much would I will be willing to pay to
avoid death well maybe I'm willing to
pay 30 bucks to avoid death if it's some
kind of Micra more thing where there is
let's say a one-in-a-million chance of
dying if that is your decision here what
that means is that on the scale from
zero to one on this standardized utility
scale thirty dollars to you is worth
zero point zero zero zero zero zero one
micromort okay Oh everyone morts which
is 1 micro more so we now have a skill
that's how much you value $30.00 we can
do this for everything for everything
you can we can say okay maybe you asked
how much they value your laptop and you
might say well maybe there's a choice or
something else maybe how much do you
value getting a new bicycle and then you
might say okay there's a choice between
getting a new bicycle or applying this
this not having to play this game and
then you say well I'd rather play the
game and have it and get the bicycle
than to not play the game you look at
the equivalence what probabilities land
on here such that you're equally happy
with one situation versus the other and
that tells you the utility value of a
bicycle a new bicycle for you how about
money isn't money away people measure
utility turns out money is
not the same as utilities for example
let's say we have a lottery some
probability of winning X 1 minus P
probability of winning Y the expected
monetary value is this quantity over
here that's averaging the money but the
utility of this lottery is this over
here so the utility of the lottery is
the weighted sum of the utilities of
each outcomes which is not the same as
the utility of the average money you
would get in fact often the utility of
the lottery will be smaller than utility
of the average money that you would get
that means most people are risk averse
and when deepened that people tend to be
risk prone let's make this a little more
explicit imagine you want to understand
utility of money this is money
this is utility how much is money worth
in utility values well who wants a
million dollars most people some people
don't you missed your chance pause okay
now the million dollars means it's worth
something positive to you cuz you like
it okay how about a billion dollars a
lot of people whoever doesn't want come
talk to me
well maybe how much is worth they get a
billion dollars well worth more how much
more well maybe some amount more now
let's think about it again now you have
your billion dollars in hand you still
want a million dollars
yeah probably you still want a million
dollars more is always better but the
first million is much more special than
once you already have the billion see
the additional value here from utility
you get from going from zero to a
million is much higher than if here you
got an extra extra million maybe I'm
only end up over here and so we see that
somehow we look at these utility curves
they end up kind of starting to saturate
not saturated but climb more slowly as
you have more and then kind of the other
way around here once you're in debt a
lot once you have lost a billion dollars
you cannot pay it off
anyway most likely so what is it to then
lose a little more it's all the same and
so that's what's happening on this side
over here how can we quantify this
imagine was a lottery between $1,000 and
0 dollars what is the expected monetary
value of $500 but most people would
prefer a guaranteed other amount would
you prefer $10.00 guaranteed over the
lottery probably not
would you prefer 900 guarantees over the
lottery yes definitely 900 guaranteed is
better than this how about 400 maybe 400
because it's guaranteed and on average
you get 500 and foreign is pretty close
and now you're guaranteed there's not
that's where most people will land
around $400 so that means is that this
certainty equivalent lies lower than the
average that's where insurance companies
come in if you are holding a lottery
ticket of this type an insurance company
will say this is worth $400 to you I'll
buy it off of you for $400 I'll take the
tickets the insurance company now has a
lottery but it has so many lotteries in
its pool of lotteries that's central
limit theorem kicks in and for the
insurance company that averages out and
that lauder take is actually worth $500
even for you it's equal in the 400 and
so that's how you actually get a win-win
situation where there's a difference
between the 400 and 500 that's where the
opportunity lives to have a win-win in
fact the insurance company gave you 450
they would still make 50 bucks on it
and so the between 4 and 500 is the
wiggle room for negotiation where all
the win wins lie between you and the
insurance company now let's take a
little test let's say you can choose win
lottery a or B a is 80% chance $4,000
20% chance nothing B is guaranteed 3,000
who prefers a who prefers B most people
prefer B here's not a lottery choice C
20% chance 4000 80% nothing versus D 25%
3,000 75% nothing who prefers C
who prefers B so most people prefer to
see that is actually pretty typical for
general population to prefer B over a
and C over D so slice also predicted
that now let's do a little bit of math
if utility of zero dollars is zero
because we can shift and rescale anyway
then be better than a means utility of
3k is better than zero point eight
utility of 4k if see better than B then
we have this equation over here that's
the exact opposite statement so people
who prefer B over a and C over D have
reached a contradiction what does that
mean it means as far as this is
concerned you had irrational preferences
because there's no utility function that
can satisfy both at the same time well
maybe there is maybe it's not that
you're irrational maybe something else
at play when you look at the utility and
people study this paradox a lot and say
well maybe it's not because people are
irrational maybe cuz we don't model the
situation the right way maybe what
happens the reason you prefer B over a
is because when a is being chosen and
you end up over here you don't just get
0 you also get a very very stupid
feeling that you could have had a lot of
money and you didn't and so there is a
zero plus stupidity here and utility of
0 plus stupidity is lower than your
Atilla t of zero and makes it all work
out again alright next time we'll look
at MVPs
really